Guide to the Suzy Harris Rytting audio-visual ski collection 1968-1991
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Suzy Harris Rytting audio-visual ski collection
1968-1991
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0622
Rytting, Suzy Harris
11 8mm films, 7 VHS videocassettes, and 1 audiocassette
The Suzy Harris Rytting audio-visual ski collection (1968-1991) consists of films and videos related to Rytting's career as a competetive skier, coach, and ski professional.
Biographical Note
Suzy Harris Rytting (b. 1930) began her early skiing outings at Alta at age 13. She started representing Alta and her high school in ski racing two years later. From the mid 1940s though the early 1950s, Suzy cut a swath through the American ski racing scene as one of the finest women racers in the country.
A two time winner of Alta's prestigious Snow Cup race in both 1947 and 1948, she also won the Mary Cornelia National Collegiate Trophy in 1947 and set a course record in Sun Valley's Gold Sun Downhill Race in 1948. She was named an alternate on the U.S. Women's Olympic Ski Team in 1948 and named to the 1950 U.S. Women's International Ski Federation (FIS) world championship ski team and the United States Winter Olympic Ski Team in 1952.
Following her ski racing career, Suzy became Secretary for the Intermountain Ski Association, a position she held from 1952 through 1959. From 1967 through 1972, she served as coach for the United Alta Skiers Junior Racing Team (ages 10-18).
Throughout her lifetime, Suzy has distinguished herself by active participation in numerous ski-related and community affairs. She currently serves as a docent, along with her husband, Bill, at the Alf Engen Ski Museum. She also continues to be a life long supporter of Alta and gives periodic ski history presentations at Alta's "Fireside Chat" program, sponsored by the Alta Historical Society.
Suzy was elected to the U.S. National Ski Hall of Fame in 1988; the Utah Sports Hall of Fame in 1988; the University of Utah Athletes Crimson Club Hall of Fame in 1991; and in 1999 was named one of Utah's "50 Greatest Athletes of the 20th Century." In 2004, Suzy Harris Rytting was also inducted into the Intermountain Ski Hall of Fame and received the S.J. Quinney Award for "enhancing the image and popularity of skiing in the region" by the J. Willard Marriott Library Ski Archives.
Biography from the Alta Historical Society.
The Suzy Harris Rytting audio-visual ski collection (1968-1991) consists of films and videos related to Rytting's career as a competetive skier, coach, and ski professional.
The materials are arranged by format type.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
See also the Suzy Harris Rytting photograph collection (P0412).
Alta (Utah); United States Ski Team; Skiing--Utah--History; Sports and Recreation; Moving images
- Family Skiing, 1968; 8mm film (Reel 1)
  Includes some footage of Suzy skiing at Monte Bondone.
- United Alta Skiers Junior Racing Team (UAS) with coaches Suzy Harris Rytting and Jim Shafer, 1969-1970; 8mm film (Reel 2)
- Gelande, Alta, 1969; 8mm film (Reel 3)
- Jackson Hole, Wyoming, 1970; 8mm film (Reel 4)
- Vacation, 1968; 8mm film (Reel 5)
- UAS 1, undated; 8mm film (Reel 6)
- UAS 3, undated; 8mm film (Reel 7)
  Snow Basin
- UAS 2, undated; 8mm film (Reel 8)
- Water skiing, 1968; 8mm film (Reel 9)
  Kalberer, Briggs, Rytting
- UAS, Logan, undated; 8mm film (Reel 10)
- Untitled film, undated; 8mm film (Reel 11)
- Suzy Harris Rytting's induction into the University of Utah's Crimson Club Hall of Fame., 1988; VHS videocassette (Cassette 12)
- Suzy Harris Rytting's induction into the U.S. Hall of Fame., undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 13)
- The United Alta Skiers at Alta, Solitude and Sundance, 1960-1970; VHS videocassette (Cassette 14)
  Suzy Harris Rytting, Jim Schater and Howard Fishman coaching
- The United Alta Skiers participating in the slalom and expert downhill competitions at Parkwest for the Junior Nationals (p.c.w.), undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 15)
- Texaco Star Award: Suzy Harris Rytting, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 16)
  2:30 minutes
- Interview with Alf Engen part 1, 1991 October 02; VHS videocassette (Cassette 17)
  Interviewers: Suzy and Bill Rytting. U.S. Forest Service Project 1991-92 By Shirley Huckins Community Library, Ketchum, Idaho.
- Interview with Alf Engen part 2, 1991 October 02; VHS videocassette (Cassette 18)
- Interview with Suzy Harris Rytting, undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 19)
  Interviewer: Bill Stearn This collection of three short pieces was originally broadcast on the radio, with radio host, Bill Stearn. The interviews detail Suzy's feelings after being told she would not be allowed to compete in the Olympics due to her early-term pregnancy.